Chris: Unit testing is an essential instrument
in the toolbox of any serious software developer.
A unit test is simply ‘a method that tests a
small portion of an application and verifies
its behaviour independently from other parts’.
Leah: A typical unit test contains 3 phases:
• First, it initializes a small piece of an
application it wants to test which is also
known as the ‘system under test’, or SUT.
• Then it applies some stimulus to the system
under test, usually by ‘calling a method on it’,
• and finally, it observes the resulting behaviour.
If the ‘observed behaviour’ is consistent
with the expectations, the unit test passes,
otherwise, it fails, indicating that there is
a problem somewhere within the unit under test.
Chris: These three ‘unit test phases’ are
also known as Arrange, Act and Assert, or AAA.
Let’s take a more detailed look at these.
Arrange, the first step of a
unit test application, is where
the test is arranged or set up.
For example, to perform the test we may need
to create an object of the targeted class,
if necessary, then we need to create mock
objects setting up variables or anything
else that may be required for the test.
Leah: Act, or the middle step of a unit step
application is where we will execute the test and
do the actual unit testing, obtaining a result.
We will call the targeted function
in this step, using the object that
we created in the previous step.
Assert, the last step of a unit test
application is where we check and verify the
returned ‘result’ with ‘expected results’
Chris: Some people also distinguish
a fourth section, ‘teardown’, which
comes after ‘Arrange, Act, and Assert’.
For example, you can use this section
to remove any files created by the test,
close a database connection, and so on.
The ‘teardown’ is usually represented
by a separate method, which is
reused across all tests in the class.
Leah: Performing unit tests can
have many advantages such as:
Making it safer and easier to refactor
the code by putting tests into a place
that make sure refactoring occurs
without problems and disruption.
It takes the risk out of
changing older source code.
Carrying out unit tests is essentially
doing quality assurance of the code.
It shows problems and bugs before
the product has an integration test.
Creating a testing process before the
coding is completed solves issues and
challenges creators, to write better code.
It can help find problems and resolve
them before further testing, so they
won’t impact other bits of code.
This includes bugs in a programmer’s execution and
issues with a specification for the unit itself.
Chris: Unit testing maps a
system and creates documentation.
It helps developers understand
the unit’s interface.
Using a unit test and good unit testing tools
means you reduce the overall cost of a project.
Early bug detection means fewer late
changes and easier to spot issues
than if it is done at a later stage.
It can also help to make you
more efficient at writing code.
When you build, run, and fix your code, you
can more quickly find and fix problems because
you are testing your code as you write it.
But, what about the disadvantages?
Leah: Unit testing is a time-consuming process.
It can take a lot of time to develop even one
small unit test, not to mention the larger ones.
Developers need to spend time on experimentation,
research, figuring out how the test method
should be structured, and what methods,
parameters, and objects, the test case needs.
It’s easy to spend an entire
day on one single ‘unit test’.
Not only is time spent creating the ‘unit
test’ itself, but also it takes time
to figure out the best way to use it.
Unit tests are problematic when you need
to test your ‘user interface’ or UI.
They are good for when you need to test business
logic implementation, but not great for UI.
Chris: Unit testing for individual components
of a software system, will catch many
errors, but they can’t catch them all.
For example, it can’t catch ‘integration bugs’
which occur when combining several units of work.
To catch an ‘integration bug’, an integration test
is needed which we cover elsewhere in this unit.
So even though there are disadvantages,
we can see that unit testing is valuable
tool to detect defects in the software,
in the early development stage.
No matter what code you are testing, finding
bugs and errors ahead of time is helpful.
If you are working with a good QA team, using
unit tests should be an efficient process
and prove helpful, if you know what to avoid.